We're a bit behind, but let's really focus and catch up. Officially
today's דף Daf is ס"ז Samech Zayin 67. We are on ס"ו
עמוד ב', Samech Vav Amud Bet, 24th day of the עומר Omer
by the way, and we actually pick up two lines from the
bottom of ס"ו... Samech Vav... the last two words on ס"ו עמוד
א'. Samech Vav Amud Aleph. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Okay now we
can turn over to ס"ו עמוד ב'. Samech Vav Amud Bet. מנא
מימרא. Mina Meila. Where do I know this from? And this is
the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava about whether we
say that you need two witnesses not only to make a קידושין
Kiddushin happen, to make a גיטין Gittin happen, but even as a
standard of proof about personal status. And one witness is not enough,
even if that witness is not contradicted. אביי Abaye said one witness
would be enough. רבא Rava said it is not. אין דבר שבערוה
פחות משנים Ein Davar Shebiervah Pachot Mishnayim translates in two ways; according
to רבא Rava you need two witnesses to make it happen and
you need two witnesses to prove that it happened. Okay, so מנא...
Mina... and this is not just about גיטין Gittin and קידושין. Kiddushin.
For example, some of the discussions were about whether a woman was
taken captive and whether that would make her אסור Assur to a
כהן, Kohen, whether a woman committed adultery and that would make her
אסור Assur to her husband. Okay, so רבא Rava says מנא מימרא,
Mina Meila, where do I know this that you need to have
two witnesses? תנן, Tnan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah. אמר רבי
שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, it's
interesting that it says תנן, Tnan, yeah, it's a משנה, Mishnah, where
is this? It's a משנה Mishnah somewhere. The side says it's also
a תוספתא. Tosefta. All right, anyway,
אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, מעשה במגורה של דיסקים, Maaseh Bemagurah
Shel Diskim, there was a story in a certain well or you
know a body of water in this place called דיסקים, Diskim, or
רש"י Rashi says it's either name of a person or the name
of a place. Okay, ביבנה, BeYavneh, in יבנה, Yavneh, שהיתה עומדת בחזקת
שלמה. shehayta omedet bechezkat sheleimah. People assumed that there was enough water
in it, it was a כשר kosher מקוה. Mikvah. ומדדו, Umadidu, and
then after you know a few months, some חכם Chacham decided to
measure it, ונמצאת חסרה venimtzeit chaseirah and it didn't have 40 סאה.
Seah. So כל טהרות שנעשו על גבה. kol taharot shena'asu algabah.
What's the status with everything that's been used in that מקוה, Mikvah,
you know all the vessels that have been dunked in the
מקוה Mikvah from the last time it was checked, when we knew
it was שלם, Shalem, and then three months later when we checked
it and we found out that it was not שלם? Shalem? So
it obviously didn't happen the first day after day one after we
measured it three months ago, so when do we assume that it
actually went under 40 סאה? Seah? So רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, so
אמר רבי טרפון מטהר, Amar Rabbi Tarfon Metaher, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
says we could assume it remained שלם Shalem until the last possible
minute, until the minute that we measured it. And anything prior to
that is okay. רבי עקיבא מטמא, Rabbi Akiva Metamei, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says no, everything that's been done since the last time we
measured it is טמא, Tamei, it's maybe not was not שלם. Shalem.
Well, exactly, so let's read that. אמר רבי טרפון, Amar Rabbi Tarfon,
מקוה זה בחזקת שלם הוא עומד. Mikvah Zeh Bechezkat Shalem Hu Omed.
What do you mean? We have a principle of חזקה, Chazakah, it
had a, you know it had a status of being full, of
being a full amount. מספק אתה בא לחסרו? Misafek Attah Ba Lechasro?
You're saying, well I don't know, maybe it may, you know way,
we don't know when it became חסר, Chaseir, when it became פסול,
Passul, so we have to say maybe it became פסול Passul way,
you know way at the beginning. You're not allowed to do that.
אל תחזירנו מספק. Al Tachazirenu Misafek.
Your doubt of when it became חסר Chaseir does not override its
status quo of being שלם. Shalem. That's a principle of a חזקה.
Chazakah. The whole point of a חזקה Chazakah is something has a
status quo. If you don't know when that status quo changed, then
you assume that it retains the status quo. So until the last
possible minute when you have a evidence that it changed, you assume
that it was שלם. Shalem. Yes, I know, we yeah. That is
the general principle of חזקה, Chazakah, that's a very reasonable position. אמר
רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says but you're
forgetting that something else here has a חזקה. Chazakah. אדם זה בחזקת
טמא הוא עומד. Adam Zeh Bechezkat Tamei Hu Omed. Any person, man,
woman who used the מקוה Mikvah before they went into the מקוה,
Mikvah, their status quo was that they were טמא. Tamei. מספק אתה
בא לטהרו? Misafek Attah Ba Letaharo? You say, well I don't know
if he became טהור. Tahor. Maybe did his status change and he
became טהור? Tahor? That depends if he was טובל tovel in a
כשר kosher מקוה. Mikvah. אל תטהרנו מספק. Al Tetaharenu Misafek.
You can't change his status if you don't know for sure that
the מקוה Mikvah was כשר. kosher. So it's a really good question,
like which one do you go by?
So אמר רבי טרפון, Amar Rabbi Tarfon, משל לעומד ומקריב על גבי
המזבח. Mashal Le'omed Umakriv Al Gabbe HaMizbeach. Let's try to analogize it
since we can't really, there's no way here to figure out which
one to tip, whether you go by the person or the מקוה,
Mikvah, let's look at an analogy. Let's say you had a person,
a כהן, Kohen, who was standing and being מקריב makriv קרבנות. Korbanot.
ונודע שהוא בן גרושה או בן חלוצה. Venoda Shehu Ben Gerusha O
Ben Chalutza. And then it was informed, somebody discovered, you know, that
his mother was divorced before being married to the father and that
he's a חלל. Challal. שעבודתו כשרה. She'avodato Kesheira. When that happens, we
say that nevertheless his עבודה avodah is כשרה kesheira until that point.
After that point it's not good. Now of course that's a really
bad analogy because then we know that he was פסול Passul before,
right? So and logically of course his עבודה avodah should have been
פסול. Passul. The גמרא's Gemara going to quote a פסוק pasuk later
on to show us that actually, you know that actually we can
say the עבודה avodah is כשרה kesheira even though we know that
he was 100% now that we have this information he was a
חלל Challal earlier. So that's like a special
גזירת הכתוב Gezeirat HaKatuv that... It seems not really at all relevant
to a question of trying to determine when something happened in the
past. Okay. It's somewhat like the question about, you know, what happens
if you're reading a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and you find that
it has a פסול, psul, and the פסול psul that did not
just happen now, like there's an extra word written in it, okay,
or a whole word is missing. So you actually don't go back
and re-read the עליה, aliyah, but that has to do with other
issues. That has to do with the fact that we can rely
on certain positions בדיעבד bedieved that you don't need a כשר kosher
תורה Torah for קריאת התורה. kerias haTorah. Okay.
But here, anyway, you you you don't re-read the עליה, aliyah, you
just finished? What?
I'm not going to go into the details, but basically correct. I
mean, it depends on the circumstances. Yes, but basically that's correct. Won't
go into- I shouldn't have brought that up. Now you're going to
ask me the specifics about that.
But anyway, okay, but but anyway, so there are some times you
don't have to go back and re-do it, but it's not because
you assume it wasn't a problem until now. There's other reasons. But
nevertheless, this is the analogy he's making. So he says, oh, you
see in that case we say it's כשר kosher moving forward. You
know, maybe he's also sort of pointing out the, you know, maybe
there's a subtext here about the social- the sort of policy consequences.
Right? Imagine the policy consequences if a כהן Kohen at the age
of 70 found out he was a בן גרושה. ben grusha. What
are you going to do, send out recall notices to everybody from
the last 50 years? Right? So there's clearly like a, you know,
even though we have to base it on a פסוק, pasuk, we
do base it on a פסוק, pasuk, but there's a reason why,
you know, we can't retroactively invalidate everything he's done. So think about
the same thing about the מקוה. mikvah. What are you going to
do? You know, everybody, you know, people, you know, women have been
with their husbands since then, people have been eating תרומה terumah all
this type of stuff, now you're going to say everything you've been
doing for the last three months is invalid? So maybe that's a
little bit of the analogy, like the sort of policy societal realities
should push us to go by the חזקה chazakah that the מקוה
mikvah was כשר kosher even though again here it's not an issue
of חזקה. chazakah. So that's what רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says.
Okay. אמר ליה רבי עקיבא. Amar lei Rabbi Akiva. אמר רבי עקיבא,
Amar Rabbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said back, no, משל
למה הדבר דומה, mashal l'ma hadavar domeh, we're going to compare it
to a כהן, Kohen, let's compare it to a כהן Kohen and
he was offering קרבנות, korbanos, ונודע שהוא בעל מום, v'noda shehu baal
mum, and here if it turns out that he had a blemish,
שעבודתו פסולה, she'avodaso pesula, it's invalid, which is like a little strange.
You would have thought that the, you know, knowing that you're a
חלל chalal is a more fundamental פסול psul than a בעל מום,
baal mum, which seems less about fundamentally about identity. And nevertheless, the
הלכה halacha is we only have a פסוק pasuk for the case
of a חלל chalal that it's not a problem what he did
in the past if it was if with ignorance. But with a
בעל מום baal mum it actually is is פסול pasul what he
did in the past. So if you're making an analogy to that
case...
What if he has a מום mum now
and we realize that he always had the מום, mum, we just
didn't know about it, right? Okay.
So what if it was like you just...
Oh, well if it was a ספק, safek, then it's even a
better proof for רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, but nevertheless he's saying
both those cases presume that it was around before, but how, you
know, but there's one case there's a הלכה halacha that you don't-
you know, you're not concerned about the past, and in this case
the הלכה halacha is you are concerned about the past.
Just the same way, let's say he broke his- let's say he
went to the doctor and he found that his arm was broken.
Yeah. So how far back do you go?
No, well that's... Okay, that's good, that would then be the debate
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon if you
didn't know how far back to go. We'd have to determine. Yeah,
I mean, but right now we're even discussing a case where it's,
again, not an exact analogy, but you found out and you knew
for sure before, and how much does that change things? Okay. אמר
רבי טרפון, Amar Rabbi Tarfon, אתה דמיתו לבעל מום
ואני דמיתיו לבן גרושה או לבן חלוצה. ata dimiso l'baal mum v'ani
dimisiv l'ben grusha o l'ben chaluza. You made the analogy to a
כהן Kohen with a מום, mum, and I made the analogy to
a כהן Kohen who was a בן גרושה, בן חלוצה. ben gerushah
ben chalutzah. נראה למי דומה. nireh l'mi domeh. Let's- great!
Let's try now- now maybe we have something to work with. Let's
try to figure out which case our מקוה mikvah case is more
similar to, even though as pointed out, it's not really similar to
either because in the מקוה mikvah case there's a ספק safek and
here there isn't a ספק. safek. Anyway, אי דומה לבן גרושה ולבן
חלוצה נדוננו כבן גרושה ובן חלוצה, ei domeh l'ben grusha v'l'ben chaluza
nedunenu k'ben grusha u'ven chaluza, if it's like the בן גרושה ben
grusha, case then then if it's more similar to that we'll apply
that law. אי דומה לבעל מום נדוננו כבעל מום, ei domeh l'baal
mum nedunenu k'baal mum, and if it's more similar in terms of
its, you know, relevant features to the בעל מום baal mum case,
we'll apply the בעל מום baal mum הלכה halacha and we'll say
that retroactively it is a problem. Okay, good. Let's talk about that
now. התחיל רבי עקיבא לדון. his'chil Rabbi Akiva ladun. So let's- so
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, okay, let's make the comparison. מקוה פסולה
ביחיד ובעל מום פסול ביחיד, mikvah pesula b'yachid u'baal mum pasul b'yachid,
ואל יוכיח בן גרושה ובן חלוצה שפסולה בשנים. v'al yochi'ach ben grusha
u'ven chaluza shepesula b'shnayim. So a מקוה mikvah is פסול, pasul, you
know, an individual can come and say, hey, I checked it and
it's and it's got a מקוה- mikvah I mean, it doesn't have
enough, and we would believe him. Normally עד אחד נאמן באיסורין, ed
echad ne'eman b'issurin, you believe an individual testimony. Similarly, if a בעל
מום baal mum comes and says, you know, if somebody says, hey,
I saw this כהן, Kohen, you know, or this כהן Kohen testifies
himself, I have a מום, mum, that would be accepted. As opposed
to the question of בן גרושה, בן חלוצה, ben gerushah ben chalutzah,
because that's a personal status issue having to do with ערוה, erva,
right? And with sex and with personal status, that requires two witnesses.
This is why we're bringing this whole discussion in. Okay, so therefore
it's of a different nature. Okay, now, it's interesting, is that just
haphazard that it's different or is that really relevant to his point?
Right? So... but we can look, we'll get back to that in
a minute. But let's just first say, so therefore, to me, it's
more similar to the בעל מום, baal mum, and therefore should be
retroactively a problem. והא הכא v'ha hacha בן גרושה ובן חלוצה ben
grusha u'ben chalutza שפסולה מאחרים, she'psula me'acherim, other people have to testify
and therefore it's less relevant. Okay, and it seems that the analogy
is, if you want to say that it's just not haphazard, you
know, oh look, I found a point of comparison, but that it's
relevant to the discussion. The point is is that like if it's
easier to establish that something is a problem, you have a lower
threshold needed to establish it's a problem, to establish that there's a
מום, mum, to establish that there's not enough water in the מקוה,
mikva, then that means that we're more prepared to apply that status
to it הלכתית, halachit, to הלכתית halachit recognize that status. So here,
where there's a question when did it become חסר, chasar, and you
have the חזקה chazaka of the person against the חזקה chazaka of
the מקוה, mikva, well in general we're more prepared to say that
we'll
acknowledge that the מקוה mikva is חסר. chasar. So therefore, that's what
we should say and we should say that everything in the past
is a problem. אמר ליה רבי טרפון, amar lei Rabbi Tarfon, רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said,
עקיבא, Akiva, כל הפורש ממך כפורש מן החיים. kol haparesh mimcha k'poresh
min hachayim. Anybody who separates from you is as if he separates
from life. It's sort of like the whole thing about the fish
on the land, right? So anyway, so okay, so anyway, so it's
funny, like, hey, like that was it. That won the case. Like
you were waiting for רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon to do a comparison
in the other direction. Anyway, fine. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says, he
gave up pretty easy. He exactly. האי בעל מום דפסולה ביחיד היכי
דמי? hai baal mum d'psula b'yachid heichi dami? What's the case of
a בעל מום baal mum that one person can testify? Now the
גמרא Gemara is talking. This is why we brought it in, to
prove that a personal status, בן גרושה ובן חלוצה, ben grusha u'ben
chalutza, needs two. Okay. So האי בעל מום דפסולה ביחיד היכי דמי?
hai baal mum d'psula b'yachid heichi dami? What does it mean that
one person can testify according to בעל מום? baal mum? אי דקא
מכחיש ליה, ei d'ka machish lei, if the guy is denying it,
no you're lying, I'm not a בעל מום, baal mum, מי מהימן,
mi meiman, we wouldn't believe the עד. ed. אלא דשתיק, ela d'shatik,
it must be that the guy is not contesting it. And therefore
we believe one by a בעל מום. baal mum. But then the
comparison is, if the בעל מום baal mum is a case of
one without being contested, ודכוותיה גבי בן גרושה ובן חלוצה דשתיק. v'dichvatah
gabei ben grusha u'ben chalutza d'shatik.
So then that means, what, meaning if the guy who has the
מום mum is מכחיש machish this one עד? ed?
Yes, then the עד ed wouldn't be believed.
But isn't this an objective thing?
We're going to get to that. Okay. Yes, we're going to get
to that, Michael. Hold off. Everything you're about to ask is coming
up. Okay, but the first what we want to prove is, what
רבא Rava is trying to prove is, is that by personal status
we would not believe one עד ed even uncontested. So he says,
and I'll show it to you. Because we say a בעל מום
baal mum works with one and בן גרושה ובן חלוצה ben grusha
u'ben chalutza two. But presumably the בעל מום baal mum with one
is uncontested because if it was contested we wouldn't believe it. So
even though we're dealing with one עד ed uncontested, we say בן
גרושה ובן חלוצה ben grusha u'ben chalutza one עד ed is not
enough. You need two. ודכוותיה גבי בן גרושה ובן חלוצה דשתיק. v'dichvatah
gabei ben grusha u'ben chalutza d'shatik. The guy is not contesting it.
וקתני מקוה פסולה ביחיד ובעל מום פסולה ביחיד והא בן גרושה ובן
חלוצה שפסולה בשנים. v'ktani mikva psula b'yachid u'baal mum psula b'yachid v'ha
ben grusha u'ben chalutza she'psula b'shnayim. And nevertheless it says even though
presumably we're dealing with a case that uncontested testimony of an עד
אחד, ed echad, by בן גרושה ובן חלוצה ben grusha u'ben chalutza
you still need two. So you see when it comes to an
issue of personal status, you need two witnesses and one uncontested witness
is not sufficient. That's רבא's Rava proof. And אביי Abaye says back
what Michael was going to say. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, no, לעולם
דקא מכחיש ליה. l'olam d'ka machish lei. No,
the guy is contesting the עד אחד ed echad who says he's
a בעל מום. baal mum. So then why do we believe
the בעל מום? baal mum? I mean, not the בעל מום, baal
mum, why do we believe the עד? ed? So then you'd say,
why would we believe the עד ed if the כהן kohen is
contesting it? דאמר ליה שלח אחוי. d'amar lei shlach achvei. Because the
עד ed says, yeah? You're telling me you're not a בעל מום?
baal mum? Strip and let's see. Okay, so that's what שלח shlach
means. שלח shlach actually can mean a Hebrew word which means like
to strip. Okay, and show, demonstrate. Okay, so you're telling me, I
say I saw you got a מום mum on your side there.
You're denying it. Let's, if you want us to believe you, strip.
Okay, so therefore in that case actually, if it, we would believe
the עד אחד ed echad even if it was contested, as long
as the guy was refusing to show. והיינו דקתני מקוה פסולה בגופו
בעל מום פסולה בגופו. v'hainu d'ktani mikva psula b'gufo baal mum psula
b'gufo.
Did we skip that line?
Yeah, before you did. Oh, I'll try and tell.
You were trying to tell me that? To tell me when you're
not asking a question, you're just something I skipped something. Okay, I
skipped down to, okay, to the דבר אחר. davar acher. I apologize.
Okay, so before the כל הפורש ממך כפורש מן החיים, kol haparesh
mimcha k'poresh min hachayim,
I'm sorry, go back. It's about five lines above the מתניתין matnitin
in רש"י. Rashi. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had two ways of
comparing it to the what do you call it,
to the בעל מום. baal mum. One was a בעל מום baal
mum it's only an עד אחד ed echad suffices and with בן
גרושה ובן חלוצה ben grusha u'ben chalutza you need two עדים. edim.
And then we'll be דבר אחר, davar acher, I, so going back,
jumping back here, another thing, another way of comparison, מקוה פסולה בגופו
בעל מום פסולה בגופו. mikva psula b'gufo baal mum psula b'gufo. The
מקוה mikva is a problem in the מקוה, mikva, there's not enough
water. The בעל מום, baal mum, the problem's on his body. ויוכיח
בן גרושה ובן חלוצה, v'yochiach ben grusha u'ben chalutza, and those are
different than the בן גרושה ובן חלוצה ben grusha u'ben chalutza case,
שפסולה she'psula מאחרים, me'acherim, that that problem comes outside of him. It's
what his parents did. And
then אמר ליה רבי טרפון. amar lei Rabbi Tarfon. So he had
two ways of comparing it to the בעל מום. ba'al mum. Number
one: בעל מום, ba'al mum, עד אחד ed echad is enough, and
same with the מקוה. mikveh. And number two: בעל מום, ba'al mum,
the problem is in the body of the person or the body
of the מקוה mikveh as opposed to בן גרושה בן חלוצה. ben
gerushah ben chalutzah So the גמרא Gemara now says, okay, so back
to where we were. So אביי Abaye was saying, no, that idea
that you would believe an עד אחד ed echad by a בעל
מום ba'al mum and not by בן גרושה בן חלוצה, ben gerushah
ben chalutzah? that's is a contested עד אחד. ed echad. And the
reason we believe him by a בעל מום ba'al mum is because
if it's not true, let the guy show it. Okay, and then
back to the גמרא, Gemara, דהיינו דקתני, dehaynu d'katani, I'm sorry to
be jumping back and forth, but back to where we were, about
eight lines before the lines get start to get wide, okay, where
it says שלח אחזי, shlach achzei, אמר ליה שלח אחזי, amar leh
shlach achzei, okay, go strip. Okay, so the yes, אביי Abaye says
we are dealing with a contested עד אחד, ed echad, but nevertheless
we believe him because he can tell the כהן, kohen, if you're
telling the truth, strip. דהיינו דקתני מקוה פסולה בגופה ובעל מום פסול
בגופו ואל יוכיח בן גרושה ובן חלוצה שפסולה מאחרים. dehaynu d'katani mikveh
psulah begufah u'va'al mum pasul begufo v'al yochi'ach ben gerushah u'ven chalutzah
shepsulah me'acherim. So that's exactly the reason he's saying by a by
a בעל מום ba'al mum we believe a contested עד אחד, ed
echad, but by a בן גרושה בן חלוצה ben gerushah ben chalutzah,
we don't believe a contested עד אחד ed echad because there's nothing
to show. How you gonna prove whether you are or aren't a
בן גרושה בן חלוצה? Ben Grusha Ben Chaluza, Right, if it's on
the body, we can say show. If I'm if the עד אחד
ed echad says, if I'm lying, show me otherwise. But by the
בן גרושה בן חלוצה, Ben Grusha Ben Chaluza if he's contested, we
won't accept the עד אחד, ed echad, right, because if I'm lying,
there's nothing to be demonstrated. All right, so that's why if it's
a contested, you need two. Okay, so is that is that sort
of clear? Right, the question here is
we've got the two עדים, edim, okay,
by the בן גרושה. ben grusha How'd you know that? I don't
know. All right, anyway, here's the case of the בן גרושה ben
grusha, and we have the two עדים. edim. And we have the
one עד, ed, here are the עדים. edim. And we have the
one עד ed by the בעל מום, ba'al mum, okay? Yeah, we
can have him that he's got some blemish on him and that
he's fighting. Okay, so the point was like this. We need two
in this case and one in this case. So the גמרא Gemara
says well presumably when one works, it's when he's uncontested. That's what
רבא Rava says because we normally wouldn't believe a contested עד. ed.
And even though one works uncontested, one uncontested does not work by
בן גרושה. ben gerushah. So you see that by personal status an
uncontested עד ed does not work. You need two עדים. edim. That's
רבא's Rava proof. And אביי Abaye says no, here he is being
contested. Okay, I can't do it anyway. He is being contested. Here
we'll just draw that they're arguing. Okay, anyway, he is being contested,
okay, he is being contested, but we still believe the עד ed
because if you're telling the truth, show us. But the and that's
why we don't believe by a בן גרושה ben gerushah because if
he's being
contested, then there's nothing that shows the עד ed is telling the
truth, there's nothing to demonstrate. Right, here if he's refusing to demonstrate
to show us, then we know that the עד ed is telling
the truth. Here, it's just he said he said there's no so
then we wouldn't believe it. So in a case of being contested,
we need two עדים edim in this case. Okay, but אביי Abaye
is saying we only need two עדים edim because it's contested. If
it was uncontested, we would accept it even in a personal status
issue.
Right. A מום mum presumably depend upon what kind of מום mum
it was, meaning if it's an internal thing, it's like you know.
Yes, an internal thing is not a מום. mum. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, it might be a טריפה treifah not
a מום. mum. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: So
it remains unproven whether we're talking about a contested עד ed or
not a contested עד ed and whether a case of personal status
we would believe an uncontested עד ed or would we always need
two עדים. edim. Now the גמרא Gemara just wraps up the issue
about the כהן. kohen. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay.
We haven't proven it. Okay. בן גרושה בן חלוצה עבודתו כשירה מנלן?
ben gerushah ben chalutzah avodato k'shirah m'nalan? How do we know this
idea that a כהן kohen who's discovered to be a בן גרושה
ben gerushah. his עבודה avodah is still כשרה, k'sherah, everything he did
until that point? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל דאמר קרא והיתה לו
ולזרעו אחריו ברית כהונת עולם, amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel d'amar kra
v'haytah lo u'l'zaro acharav berit kehunat olam,
right by פינחס. Pinchas. It should be for him and his future
seed ברית כהונת עולם. berit kehunat olam. בין זרע כשר בין זרע
פסול. bein zera kasher bein zera pasul. זרעו zaro means any of
his descendants or male descendants whether כשר kasher or בין זרע פסול.
bein zera pasul. So it'll be this idea that he has a
status of כהן kohen even if it turned out that he was
a חלל, chalal, which is kind of shocking because a חלל chalal
you feel fundamentally doesn't have the קדושת כהונה. kedushat kehunah. אבי דשמואל
אמר מהכא ברך ה' חילו ופעל ידיו תרצה. avi d'Shmuel amar me'hacha
barech Hashem cheilo u'fo'al yadav tirtzeh. This is by the לוי. Levi.
Bless his service strength, so what does that mean? And the act
of his hands, ופעל ידיו תרצה, u'fo'al yadav tirtzeh, by the way,
רצוי retzuy by קרבנות, korbanot, right, לרצון להם לפני ה'. l'ratzon lahem
lifnei Hashem.
So חז"ל Chazal read this very much in the context of קרבנות
korbanot and פעל ידיו po'al yadav bringing מקריב makriv the קרבן. korban.
And it's ברך ה' חילו, barech Hashem cheilo, אפילו חולין שבו. afilu
chulin shebo. So the חילו cheilo is a play on words, even
if it turns out that he doesn't have קדושה, kedusha, even it
turns out that he's a חלל. chalal. תרצה, tirtzeh, only until that
point. Then they'll know, but what? Right, obviously, obviously. So we read
it in that context when we were ignorant of it, until the
point that we found out. רבי ינאי אמר מהכא ובאת אל הכהן
אשר יהיה בימים ההם. Rabbi Yannai amar me'hacha u'vata el hakohen asher
yihyeh bayamim hahem. וכי תעלה על דעתך שאדם הולך אצל כהן שלא
היה בימיו? v'chi ta'aleh al da'atcha she'adam holech eitzel kohen shelo hayah
b'yamav? What do you mean go to the... What other כהן kohen
you gonna go to? אלא זה כשר ונתחלל. Ela zeh kasher venitchalel.
So it means, okay, it turned out that that's who you had
even though he was a חלל, chalal, but nevertheless it's still good.
Okay, as long as you didn't know at the time and he
didn't know. But what?
Is this the same that's father Shmuel is actually giving honor to
Shmuel?
Is that what it is? No, he always called him אבוה דשמואל.
Avuha de'Shmuel. I'm not exactly sure why. Okay. בעל מום דעבודה פסולה
מנלן? Baal mum de'avoda pesula minalan? So how do you know that
this does not apply to a
בעל מום? baal mum? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל דאמר קרא,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel de'amar krah, the verse says, לכן אמור
הנני נותן לו את בריתי שלום, Lachen emor hineni noten lo et
briti shalom, by again going back to פינחס. Pinchas. כשהוא שלם, Kshehu
shalem, this idea that it works for his זרע zera even if
it's חלל, chalal, that's only if he is שלם, shalem, only if
he is unblemished. ולא כשהוא חסר, Velo kshehu chaser, not when he's
lacking. והא שלום כתיב, Ve'ha shalom ketiv, but it says שלום, shalom,
not שלם. shalem. אמר רב נחמן ו דשלום קטיעה היא. Amar Rav
Nachman Vav de'shalom ketia hi. No, the ו vav is like not
a full, we there's a special way we write the ו, vav,
we don't write the full length of the leg, and that's to
indicate that actually to make that
דרשה. drasha. Anyway, so anyway, that's that funny הלכה. halacha. I do
have to tell you that I find this, I mean I don't,
I can't, A, I just don't understand the logic of it just
from even a purely הלכתית halachic standpoint. A חלל chalal doesn't have
any קדושה. kedusha. A בעל מום baal mum does. A בעל מום
baal mum can't you know, מטמא למתים, mitameh le'metim, can't marry the
women a כהן kohen can't marry. A חלל chalal has none of
those restrictions. A בעל מום baal mum shares in the קרבנות, korbanot,
we just read it in the previous פרשה, parsha, right, that he's
חלק כחלק יאכלו. chelek ke'chelek yocheilu. No, that was a different פסוק.
pasuk. Anyway, but the פסוק pasuk says that a בעל מום baal
mum shares in the קרבנות korbanot and obviously a בן גרושה ben
gerushah does not. And nevertheless, when it turns out that it was
something you didn't, that you didn't know about, it's okay in one
and not the other. The best I could say is similar to
the גמרא's Gemara point before about, you know, שטרות ושואות, shtarot u'sho'ot,
that in one case it was discoverable and it was something that,
you know, it was not like this abstract knowledge thing, you know,
it was actually something that we could have, you know, that was
like present to be seen, so that somehow more marks it and
we should have seen it, you know, and that maybe more makes
for the problem. But I really find a hard time to understand
this and particularly if you, you know, to argue that like it's
if if the argument is that a מום mum is like somehow
more of like less objectionable than the בן גרושה ben gerushah בן
חלוצה, ben chaluza. you know, that raises all these other issues that
I have. So anyways, questions that I have. Yes, Charles?
Two questions. Is that ו vav really not a full ו vav
in our current ספרי תורה? Sifrei Torah? I think it's left off
on more than one.
What what is it, it looks like a י? yud?
It looks like a י. yud.
Well, it depends. There's different ways of doing the ו קטיעה. vav
ketia.
Right. There's some people read it like a line between, right?
Different ways of doing it.
You have a broken ו. vav.
Or smaller, like doesn't go all the way down to the ground.
Right, yeah.
And the ספר תורה Sefer Torah is still כשר. kasher.
Yeah, because that's the מסורה masora of how to write it.
Okay, some second, more important, maybe more important question. This does seem
to have, this debate, which they don't seem to have fully resolved,
would seem to have issues regarding a convert proving his
Jewish...
Right, so I've been translating, it's a good question, I've been translating
אין דבר שבערוה פחות משנים Ein davar she'be'erva pachot mi'shnayim as personal
status. There is some question about that and you're right and about
how to look at the whole, like, you know, convert case etc.
and by convert to make the conversion take place, you don't need
two, you need three, you need a בית דין. Beit Din. And
then the question becomes right about the issue you raised, exactly that
about proving it. So that is a good point. We do generally,
we basically פוסק posken like רבא Rava against אביי, Abaye, which is
a good thing, אין דבר שבערוה פחות משנים Ein davar she'be'erva pachot
mi'shnayim even in terms of proving it because all the cases in
the גמרא Gemara basically were to invalidate people. Okay, but it could
also make it a question about sometimes it's in the flip. A
woman needs to prove that she's divorced. What level of proof does
she need to produce that she's divorced? Or somebody has to prove
that they've converted, right? I mean, so these are you know, so
that's those are good questions. But we basically פוסקים poskim like רבא.
Rava. Let's just start, let's just go on. Let's get to the
next משנה. mishna. Okay, כל מקום, Kol makom, let's start the next
משנה. mishna. כל מקום שיש קידושין ואין עבירה הולד הולך. Kol makom
she'yesh kiddushin ve'ein aveira ha'valad holech.
Now we're getting to the inter the whole issue in קידושין kiddushin
about about like ייחוס, yichus, about identity, you know, which is has
to do with like you know and all these פסולים, psulim, ממזר
mamzer and we just mentioned בן גרושה Ben Grusha בן חלוצה ben
chaluza, for כהן, kohen, but you know all this question about what
is your I there's gotta be a word here, not identity and
not exactly status, but you know some how your your class? What
word would you use to describe questions like כהן לוי ישראל, kohen
Levi Yisrael, you know, ממזר? mamzer? Caste? Caste?
Genealogy? Geneaological? Caste? Caste? We're into caste and we're like it's a
little weird because it implies that... Yeah, exactly. It really is like
a caste. We said category?
Yeah, personal status category? Genealogy? All right, okay, genealogical status, ייחוס. yichus.
Let's say ייחוס. yichus. Anyway, okay. So anyway, let's take a look.
Okay. So כל מקום שיש קידושין ואין עבירה. Kol makom she'yesh kiddushin
ve'ein aveira.
If if if it's a mar if it's two, you know, man
and a woman and קידושין kiddushin is binding if there could be
קידושין kiddushin even if קידושין kiddushin didn't take place but if it's
legally there could be marriage between them. And there is no sin
that took place in their union, okay, which is hopefully a standard
case, הולד הולך אחר הזכר. havelad holeich achar hazachar.
So it's the status passes on is defined by the father, okay,
by the male of that of that pair. ואיזה ve'ezeh what would
be a scenario of this? זה כהנת לויה וישראלית zeh kohenes leviya
veYisraeleet whether the the woman could is in either כהן לוי ישראל,
kohen levi yisrael שנסאו לכהן לוי וישראל shenisu lekohen levi veYisrael and
the man is כהן kohen לוי levi ישראל. Yisrael, So what's the
status of the child? Simple question. How what's the status of the
child? It goes by the status of the father. If the status
is a כהן kohen the kid's a כהן, kohen status of the
father is a לוי levi the kid's a לוי. levi It doesn't
matter what the mother is, it goes by the father. Okay, that's
קידושין kidushin is binding and there was no עבירה. aveira. וכל מקום
שיש קידושין ויש עבירה vekol makom sheyesh kidushin veyesh aveira now if
their קידושין kidushin is binding but it's in but it's in transgression,
הולד הולך אחר הפגום havelad holeich achar hapagum
then it's the child goes by the invalidity, by the stigma, meaning
it doesn't matter mother or father, you know, the the stigma passes
on to the child. ואיזה ve'ezeh what would be that case? זה
אלמנה לכהן גדול גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט zeh almanah lekohen gadol grusha
vechalutza lekohen hedyot first of all any of the forbidden כהן kohen,
relationships, an אלמנה almanah with a כהן גדול kohen gadol or גרושה
וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט grusha vechalutza lekohen hedyot there it's not actually the
status, the kid doesn't become a גרושה, grusha, but what we say
is because it is a forbidden union for a כהן kohen the
kid becomes a חלל, chalal, okay, so that the kid gets affected
regardless either way, okay, but then the idea as the concept of
the of the of the stigma passes on, that's more directly applicable
to the next case. בת ישראל לממזר ונתין bas Yisrael lemamzer venetin
oh I'm sorry I skipped it. ממזרת ונתינה וישראל mamzeret venetina veYisrael
if the woman is a ממזרת mamzeret or נתינה netina which is
the Gibeonites and I'm not going to have a little bracket the
נתינים netinim for now but let's just say ממזרת. mamzeret. A woman
is a ממזרת mamzeret who marries a male who is not a
ממזר mamzer or the reverse, a man is a ממזר mamzer who
marries a female who is not, okay, ממזרת ונתינה וישראל mamzeret venetina
veYisrael did I just say the same thing twice? Anyway fine. Okay,
the woman is the ממזרת mamzeret and marries a man who is
not or בת ישראל לממזר ונתין bas Yisrael lemamzer venetin the woman
is a is not a ממזרת mamzeret and she marries a man
who is, then the child is a ממזר. mamzer. Okay, so marriage
is binding because marriage is binding by the איסורי לאוין issurei lavin
if it's not כרת karet or מיתה mitah it's a binding marriage
if it's just a לאו, lav, okay, but nevertheless the child gets
the you know disqualified status. The child becomes a חלל chalal in
the case of כהנים kohanim and the child becomes a ממזר mamzer
if one of the parents is a
ממזר. mamzer. וכל מי שאין לה עליו קידושין vekol mi she'ein lah
alav kidushin any woman for whom קידושין kidushin is not binding אבל
יש לה על אחרים קידושין aval yesh lah al acherim kidushin she
could marry somebody else. She just can't marry him. יש לה על
אחרים yesh lah al acherim other people can marry her. Regarding her
other people can whatever it's a funny construct but anyway other people
can marry her. Okay, הולד ממזר. havelad mamzer. The child is a
ממזר. mamzer. This is the general point that עריות arayot the child
is a ממזר. mamzer. Now who is this woman? What what does
it mean? Because ואיזה ve'ezeh who is this? זה הבא על אחת
מכל העריות שבתורה. zeh haba al achat mikol ha'arayot shebaTorah. Either she's
a married woman, okay, then other people can marry her like her
husband, okay, she's married to him and then or she's a sister,
a mother, a daughter and other people can marry her. So basically
it means any woman who's of so who does it exclude? Who's
a woman that nobody could marry? Okay, so that is the last
case. וכל מי שאין לה לא עליו ולא על אחרים קידושין vekol
mi she'ein lah lo alav velo al acherim kidushin any woman who
can't be married to anybody הולד כמותה havelad kamosah the child follows
the mother's status but is not a ממזר. mamzer. ואיזה ve'ezeh זה
ולד שפחה ונכרית. zeh velad shifcha venochrit. A non-Jewish woman or a
slave, right? There's no קידושין kidushin I mean non-Jews have you know
בני נח Bnei Noach but for us as Jews no Jew can
marry a woman who is not Jewish. No Jew can marry a
woman who is a slave. So therefore in that case there's no
קידושין kidushin but nevertheless the child isn't a ממזר mamzer the child
is either a non-Jew or a slave depending on who the mother
is. And this is basically the principle of matrilineal descent, okay. So
you're about to be not today but soon we're going to actually
be looking at the prime גמרא Gemara about the issue of matrilineal
descent. The father is Jewish or the mother isn't Jewish, right? It
goes by it goes that way as if it was the reverse,
right? If the mother was Jewish and the father was not, either
way it says I mean that's not exactly covered in the משנה
Mishna but either way the principle is הולד כמותה, havelad kamosah, okay.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagrees with this משנה Mishna
because he would say ממזר mamzer is even by חייבי לאוין, chayvei
lavin, yes.
But it is covered, right? Because she could be the קידושין kidushin
would hold with someone else, but not not with him.
Yeah, but then but if we were to follow that logic we
would say that then it would be a ממזר, mamzer, which we
don't say, right. So it's because it's really the last part until
then it was sort of balanced men and woman, the last part
sort of focuses totally on the woman. Right. Yeah. Because yeah because.
But the first part is really by the father, right?
Well, the first part says you go by the father and then
it says or you go by if there if קידושין kidushin is
binding but it's an עבירה aveira you go by either parent, but
then one was describing but that was describing the scenario equally from
her perspective and his perspective. In the end it was totally from
her perspective. If it's a woman with whom קידושין kidushin isn't binding
but she can marry somebody else it's a ממזר, mamzer, if it's
a woman with whom קידושין kidushin isn't binding and she can't marry
somebody
else. It doesn't talk about the the Jewish woman and the non-Jewish
man, isn't like covered in the description of this משנה. Mishnah. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. כל מקום שיש קידושין. Kol
makom sheyesh kiddushin. אמר ליה Amar lei Rabbi Shimon le-Rabbi Yochanan, כללא
הוא? klala hu? Does this real principle work? Now we're going to
have a fun thing and point out all the things not in
the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, דכל מקום שיש קידושין ואין עבירה הולד הולך
אחר הזכר, de-kol makom sheyesh kiddushin ve-ein aveirah havlad holech achar hazachar,
that whenever קידושין kiddushin is binding and there's no transgression you follow
the father. הרי גר, Harei ger, how about a case of a
convert who נשא ממזרת, nasa mamzeres, married a ממזרת, mamzeres, because there's
an opinion that by the מאן ד mon de that the ממזר
mamzer is allowed to marry a
גר. ger.
Okay, so that's...
yeah, that is way we פוסקין, pasken, but it's a debate in
the גמרא. Gemara. ויש קידושין ואין עבירה, Ve-yesh kiddushin ve-ein aveirah, קידושין
kiddushin is binding, there's no sin, והולד הולך אחר הפגם, ve-havlad holech
achar hapagam,
and nevertheless, even when you do this, the child still is a
ממזר, mamzer, which is really unfortunate, or else that'd be a great
way to solve the ממזר mamzer problem. Right? But we say the
child follows. So here's a case, no עבירה, aveirah, and it doesn't
go by the father, it goes by whichever party is the ממזר,
mamzer, the child's a ממזר. mamzer. Doesn't matter about the father.
דתניא, Detanya, גר שנשא ממזרת, ger shenasa mamzeres, if a גר ger
marries a woman who is a ממזרת, mamzeres, הולד ממזר. havlad mamzer.
You don't go by the father, the child's a ממזר, mamzer, it
always goes by the ממזר mamzer status. דברי רבי יוסי. Divrei Rabbi
Yose. That's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so he said, so he said, so that doesn't fit in our
משנה. Mishnah. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so who is this... so Rabbi Yochanan said back
to Rabbi Shimon, or... so אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back
to him, מי סברת מתניתין רבי יוסי היא? mi savart masnitin Rabbi
Yose hi? Who says that משנה Mishnah is רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose?
מתניתין רבי יהודה היא, masnitin Rabbi Yehuda hi, maybe it's רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda who disagrees with רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. What does רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say? דאמר, De-amar, גר לא ישא ממזרת, ger lo
yisa mamzeres, a גר ger is not allowed to marry a ממזרת.
mamzeres. So רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda fundamental argument with רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose is not about the status of the child, it's whether a
גר ger is allowed to marry a ממזרת mamzeres or not. So
he says a גר ger is not allowed to marry a ממזרת.
mamzeres. And then it fits the categories because if that marriage was
forbidden, the child goes by the invalidity, goes by the stigma. Okay?
ויש קידושין ויש עבירה, Ve-yesh kiddushin ve-yesh aveirah, so according to רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it is in transgression, and once it's in transgression,
it completely fits our משנה, Mishnah, הולד הולך אחר הפגם, havlad holech
achar hapagam, then it goes by the stigma. Okay, so that fits
our כלל. klal. But we're going to have a problem now with
everything that wasn't mentioned in the משנה. Mishnah. Either it's an exception
and the משנה's Mishnah כלל klal isn't right, or if it's not
an exception, why wasn't it included in the examples? Okay, so we're
not going to be happy either way. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says fine, you're telling me that that case fits, ממזר וגר
mamzer ve-ger according to the opinion that that's forbidden, the child is
a ממזר, mamzer, why wasn't that listed as an example? So the
גמרא Gemara says,
where were we, ונתנייה, venitnai, for list it? Okay, so גמרא Gemara
says no. תנא כל מקום לאתויי. Tanna kol makom l'atuyei. That's why
it has a general statement, כל מקום, kol makom, right? It says
כל מקום kol makom if you take a look, it starts by
saying כל מקום שיש קידושין ואין עבירה, kol makom sheyesh kiddushin ve-ein
aveirah, and then it has כל מקום שיש קידושין ויש עבירה. kol
makom sheyesh kiddushin ve-yesh aveirah. So the כל מקום kol makom of
יש קידושין ויש עבירה yesh kiddushin ve-yesh aveirah includes the case of
a ממזר וגר. mamzer ve-ger. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, לעולם רבי
יוסי היא, l'olam Rabbi Yose hi, or you know what, let's go
back. We could go like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and we could
say it is an exception. Okay, there is an exception to the
rule.
ואיזו זו? Ve-eizu zu?
Well, that's exactly, thank you, that's exactly where we're going to get
to. Okay, it is רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, you're right, it is
an exception, okay, so how do I deal with the fact that
there's an exception to the rule, that there could be a case
of no עבירה aveirah and the kid still carries the stigma? Because
as Michael said, ותנא איזו זו למעוטי, vetana eizu zu lema'utei, because
ואיזו זו ve-eizu zu is telling you this כלל klal does not
totally true. Here is the list that it applies to. It's not,
you can't assume that this rule applies to everything. Okay, so basically
what we're going to do is, okay, we're going to have to
start adding cases and decide which thing, okay? So we've got כל
מקום, kol makom, you know, אין עבירה, ein aveirah, I'll just put
that, right, it goes by the זכר, zachar, it goes by the
man, and we basically have, you know, כהן kohen לוי levi. ישראל
Yisrael. case, okay? And then but then we said, but then what
we're going to say is,
you know,
ואיזו, ve-eizu, I'm trying to figure out how to draw this on
the board. Anyway, first we have this, we have the ואיזו זו,
ve-eizu zu, the גמרא's Gemara going to say ואיזו זו ve-eizu zu
means since I'm giving the list, it means there are some exceptions.
That's what the גמרא's Gemara going to assume, right? Here's the כלל,
klal, here's the list. The list indicates what are the exceptions. So
here we're going to have... here are going to be the exceptions
indicated by the word ואיזו זו. ve-eizu zu. Okay, and the כל
מקום kol makom was the כלל klal and that's going to allow
us to say other things that should have been on the list,
we didn't mention, well, that's the כלל klal is coming to tell
us. ואיזו זו Ve-eizu zu allows us to say it's not everything
and there are some
exceptions. does not list all cases. There are other cases that should
have been included as a good application of the rule, and there
are other cases that are an exception to the rule, and we're
going to have to deal with the fact that none of those
are in the משנה. Mishna. So where we're basically going to wind
up saying is, anything that fits the rule, we're going to say
it was included in the כלל, klal, כל מקום. kol makom. Anything
that's an exception to the rule, we're going to say because it
said איזו זו eizo zo which was saying no, it's only here's
the application means there's some things that are exceptions to the rules.
Okay? So we're going to use those phrases to deal with everything
that's not in the משנה. Mishna. Okay? And by the way, we're
going to apply it to the end part, כל מקום שיש עבירה
kol makom she'yesh aveira because הולך אחר הפגם, holech achar hapgam, okay?
Right? That's what the second part said. And then it said ואיזו
זו, ve'eizo zo, right? ואיזו זו. ve'eizo zo. So it has it
here too. Okay, rule, exception.
Okay, so now, okay, this is where it goes by הזכר hazachar
and this is where it goes by הפגם. hapgam. Okay, so now
because each one says here's the rule and here's the list, it's
going to allow us to put missing things in either of those
categories. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, so where does the issue
of what do you call it סוגיא sugya about a גר וממזרת?
ger umamzeret? Okay, so גר וממזרת, ger umamzeret, where does גר וממזרת
ger umamzeret go? So either גר וממזרת ger umamzeret get added here
because they apply to the rule of go after the פגם pgam
if there's an עבירה. aveira. That's according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
Or if there's no עבירה, aveira, then they're an exception to the
rule and they go under here, רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, גר וממזרת,
ger umamzeret, because they're an exception to the rule. No עבירה aveira
and it still goes by the פגם. pgam. You see what we're
doing? Yes? I'm not asking if you're happy with it, but you
see what we're doing? Okay. All right. Anyway, ופסולא, upsulo, so now
that's going to be the rest of this דף, daf, basically saying
everything not listed either works with the rule or is an exception
and it fits into one of these phrases.
Okay, ופסולא, upsulo, and nothing else, והרי חלל שנשא בת ישראל, ve'harei
chalal she'nasa bat Yisrael, a חלל chalal marries a בת ישראל, bat
Yisrael, ויש קידושין ואין עבירה. ve'yesh kiddushin ve'ein aveira. Now the גמרא'ס
Gemara's primarily looking to find exceptions, obviously that's more interesting.
Okay, חלל שנשא בת ישראל, chalal she'nasa bat Yisrael, that קידושין kiddushin
is binding, there's no sin for a חלל כהן chalal Kohen to
marry a
non-כהן Kohen woman. Okay, it's totally מותר, mutar, קידושין kiddushin is binding,
והולד הולך אחר הזכר, ve'havalad holech achar hazachar, and the child, oh
no, actually this isn't an exception, this is actually the rule. Okay,
and the child follows the father. Okay, wait, what's the problem here?
חלל שנשא, chalal she'nasa, ויש קידושין ואין עבירה, ve'yesh kiddushin ve'ein aveira,
הולד הולך אחר הזכר. havalad holech achar hazachar. Yeah, and why is
that a problem? That actually fits.
Is that a proof that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi could be right,
that there are things that we haven't listed?
Right.
Yeah,
one minute,
hold on.
Oh, the problem is that this is, oh, oh, the problem is,
okay, I got the problem. The problem is that this is a
case of a פגם, pgam, and the פגם, pgam, meaning it is
true
that, wait minute, hold on, ואיזו
זו
ופסולא,
ve'eizo
zo upsulo, והרי
חלל
שנשא בת ישראל,
ve'harei chalal she'nasa
bat
Yisrael, ויש קידושין ואין עבירה, ve'yesh kiddushin ve'ein aveira, הולד הולך אחר
הזכר. havalad holech achar hazachar. Yeah, and why is that a problem?
That actually fits. It's just a bummer that it's not listed?
It's against רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi because he's saying all of the
things should be listed, ואיזו זו, ve'eizo zo, right?
No,
we're just saying the one exception falls into the ואיזו זו. ve'eizo
zo.
Oh, I guess that's, yeah, saying ואיזו זו
ve'eizo zo is to confine it to just those things listed.
Oh,
I see your point. That now we're assuming, because I already jumped
ahead where the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to use all the categories, but
you're saying, I see your point. You're saying at this stage we're
assuming ואיזו זו, ve'eizo zo, I think you're right, I think you're
right. Okay, so I jumped ahead to assume we're going to use
all of the categories to deal with all the problems, but I
think Jenna is correct that the גמרא Gemara at this stage is
assuming that ואיזו זו ve'eizo zo means it's only these things that
are listed and we're not looking at the כלל klal according to
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. So if it's only these things that are
listed that are the application of the rule, here's another application of
the rule. Okay, yeah, thank you, that's right. והרי ופסולא, ve'harei upsulo,
are you telling me it's only these things that are listed that
are the application of the rule? והרי חלל שנשא בת ישראל, ve'harei
chalal she'nasa bat Yisrael, דאית קידושין ולית עבירה, de'it kiddushin ve'leit aveira,
so that's a permissible marriage, והולד הולך אחר הזכר ve'havalad holech achar
hazachar and the child follows the father's status. So ואיזו זו, ve'eizo
zo, it's not a complete list. You're right, it's not a complete
list. So
the גמרא Gemara says הא לא קשיא, ha la kashya, that's not
a
problem. כרבי דוסתאי בן רבי יהודה. ke'Rabbi Dostai ben Rabbi Yehuda. Like
רבי דוסתאי בן רבי יהודה. Rabbi Dostai ben Rabbi Yehuda. and the
ואיזה זו ve'eizo zo is a complete list. סבירא ליה. svira lei.
Okay, so now you're right, now at this stage I jumped too
far ahead. At this stage we're asserting that the ואיזה זו ve'eizo
zo means there are exceptions and איזה זו eizo zo is telling
you it's only this list and nothing else is an application of
the rule. So the גמרא Gemara says והרי ישראל שנשא חללה, ve'harei
Yisrael shenasa chalala, one minute, how about a ישראל Yisrael who married
a woman who's a חללה, chalala, which is permissible, he's not a
כהן. Kohen. דיש קידושין ואין עבירה הולד הולך אחר הזכר de'yesh kiddushin
ve'ein aveira havlad holech achar hazachar and the child is not a
חלל. chalal. The child is כשר. kasher. Okay, because he's a ישראל.
Yisrael. ישראל Yisrael married a חללה, chalala, the child is a חללה,
chalala, the child is כשר. kasher. So that's a case where it
goes by the male, so how can you say, yeah, how can
you say איזה זו eizo zo is the entire application of the
list? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תנא, tana, now he said
what I was jumping ahead of. כל מקום דרישא לאתויי. kol makom
de'reisha le'atuyei. Fine. The כל מקום דרישא kol makom de'reisha allows for
us to both deal with things that are applications not included and
to deal with exceptions. Okay? So the כל מקום kol makom now
of the רישא, reisha, right? The כל מקום kol makom of the
רישא reisha is going to include what? So this, so the exception
is גר וממזרת. ger u'mamzeret. That's a case where there is no
עבירה aveira and it goes by the פסול pasul and the case
that's not listed that should have been here is ישראל וחללה Yisrael
ve'chalala or we can now also include חלל וישראלית, chalal ve'Yisraelit, right,
where, where in those types of cases no עבירה aveira and the
child actually would go by the father. Okay, so those are other
applications of the rule, right? So we were starting that it was
correct assuming that there's only, you know, there are no more applications
of the rule, everything else is an exception. And now we're saying
actually there's some things that are applications we didn't include and there's
some exceptions. Applications we didn't include: no עבירה aveira and it goes
by the father is the חלל chalal situation. It always goes by
the father.
Not like רבי דוסא. Reb Dosi. I know, but once we give
this answer, we don't have to say that. We always go by
the father. No עבירה aveira we go by the father. There are
cases no עבירה aveira we go by the פסול, pasul, that's the
גר וממזרת. ger u'mamzeret. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, וניתני בהדיא. u'nitnei be'hedya.
You say you go by the father, חלל וישראלית chalal ve'Yisraelit and
the kid would be כשר לכהונה? kasher li'khuna?
If it's a חלל וישראלית, chalal ve'Yisraelit, what do you mean?
You listed חלל וישראלית. chalal ve'Yisraelit. Right. והולד הולך אחר, ve'havlad holech
achar, oh right, הזכר, hazachar,
right, so he would be a חלל. chalal. Yeah. And ישראל וחללה,
Yisrael ve'chalala, the ולד vlad would be כשר. kasher.
Right. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says וניתני בהדיא. u'nitnei be'hedya. So if
there are things that are included in the list, I get that
you don't want to list exceptions. You want to try to create
a כלל. klal. But why not say more of the applications explicitly?
Okay, why not say them explicitly? משום דלא מתני ליה mishum de'lo
matnei lei because you can't say it easily in the way the
משנה Mishna is phrased. היכי ניתני? heichi nitnei? How should you say
it? כהנת לוי וישראלית וחללה
שנשאו לכהן לוי וישראל. kohenet levi ve'Yisraelit ve'chalala shenasu le'kohen levi ve'Yisrael.
Okay, that's how you would want to say it, right? If you
wanted to include the חללה chalala in that. But you can't frame
it that way, because then you're including the possibility that a חללה
chalala could marry a כהן. Kohen. דחללה לכהן לא חזיא. de'chalala le'kohen
lo chazya. It doesn't fit neatly in the framing of the משנה,
Mishna, which is a pretty good answer. Okay? So in the case
of כהן לוי וישראל, kohen levi ve'Yisrael, we could have included a
חללה chalala with a ישראל Yisrael or a חלל, chalal, I mean
with a ישראלית Yisraelit or a חללה chalala with a ישראל, Yisrael,
but it wouldn't have been easy to fit that into the משנה
Mishna in one sentence.
You'd have to say it.
Okay, we want to make a tight little teaching of the משנה.
Mishna. Okay, so now we've allowed for the fact that there are
things that are part of the כלל klal we didn't list and
there are exceptions to the כלל. klal. ואיכא דרבה בר בר חנה,
ve'ika de'Rabba bar bar Chana, how about רבה בר בר חנה? Rabba
bar bar Chana? דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, de'amar
Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, מצרי שני שנשא מצרית ראשונה
בנה שלישי הוי. Mitzri sheini shenasa Mitzrit rishona benah shelishi havei. Okay,
so, so the הלכה halacha is that a מצרי Mitzri until the
third generation of... a מצרי Mitzri converts, now he's a first generation,
or she. His child or her child is a second generation מצרי.
Mitzri. Only a third generation, דור שלישי יבא להם בקהל השם. dor
shelishi yavo lahem bi'khal Hashem. Now how do you count generations? Let's
say you have a first generation מצרי, Mitzri, right, I'm sorry, a
second generation מצרי Mitzri marrying, a man, marrying a first generation מצרית.
Mitzrit. Is the child a third generation or a second generation? Got
the question? Okay, so the הוי havei says, מצרית ראשונה בנה שלישי,
Mitzrit rishona benah shelishi, the child goes by the father presumably and
it's a third generation. So there you have a case of it's
מותר mutar for a מצרי Mitzri to marry a מצרית, Mitzrit, they
all converts here, okay? It's מותר mutar for them to marry one
another, והולד הולך אחר הזכר. ve'havlad holech achar hazachar. The generations are
counted based on the father. So that's another application of this rule
of מצרי Mitzri and מצרית Mitzrit that we should go by the
father. Why was that not listed? So the גמרא Gemara says you
know what? הוי תנא כל מקום דרישא לאתויי. hovei tana kol makom
de'reisha le'atuyei. Fine. That's what the כל מקום kol makom is doing.
We're now allowing ourselves to both deal with things that are applications
not included and to deal with exceptions. to say anything that wasn't
listed is included in the כל מקום. kol makom. You're right, that's
another application of the rule. Okay, ולדמי דאמר שני הוי, u'ledimi d'amar
sheini havi, how about רב דימי Rav Dimi that says the opposite,
you go by the mother in the case of מצרי Mitzri and
מצרית? Mitzrit? So, so what's the answer? תנא איזו זו למעוטי. Tana
eizo zo l'motei. Okay, so according to some, that would be it's
either the rule or the exception. So now it's perfect. Anything that's
a rule that we didn't list is included in כל מקום. kol
makom. Anything that's an exception that we didn't list is included in
איזו זו. eizo zo.
Well, the rule is still generally true, but yes. I know. The
best thing is to do, is there's two parts. One is the
literary question of, it doesn't fit. The other question is the legal
question, is this rule at all helpful? So if we can make
the exceptions as narrow as possible, then we can tolerate some exceptions
if the rule is generally true. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like
this: ואיכא, v'ika, what about the case of דכי אתא רבין אמר
רבי יוחנן d'ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan באומות הלך אחר הזכר?
b'umot halach achar hazachar?
If you have two non-Jews,
and the case we're going to see is a כנעני K'na'ani and
a non-כנעני, K'na'ani, right? So, and what would you consider the child?
You know, what tribe would the child be? Would it be a
כנעני? K'na'ani? And the הלכה halacha is about כנענים, K'na'anim, you know,
or would it be a non? So no, you go by the
father. Okay, that's fine. נתגיירו, Nitgayru, now let's say they've converted, okay,
and you have to decide the status of the child. It could
also be a מואבי Moavi and an אדומי Edomi where there're different
הלכות halachot about whether, when you can marry into them, right? Even
after they've converted. So he says, הלך אחר הפגום שבשניהם. halach achar
hapagam shebishneihem. So you go by the פגום. pagum. Now, if you
have a converted אדומי Edomi marrying a converted מצרי, Mitzri, it's אין
עבירה, ein aveira, it's like מצרי Mitzri and מצרית, Mitzrit, יש קידושין
ואין עבירה, yesh kiddushin v'ein aveira, they're both converted, and it says
you go by the פגום. pagum. So that's an exception to the
rule, right? אין עבירה יש קידושין ein aveira yesh kiddushin and you're
going by the פגום. pagum.
Well, okay, so the גמרא Gemara will say because if one of
them has a more disqualifying status. Okay, we'll see it in the
גמרא. Gemara. But it would be a case where one of them
has a more disqualifying status than the other. Right, exactly, exactly. So
we'll see it in the גמרא. Gemara. So you go by the
most disqualifying status of the two. So that's an exception to the
rule. So the גמרא Gemara says, תנא איזו זו למעוטי, Tana eizo
zo l'motei, fine. So here not only is an exception possibly מצרי
Mitzri and מצרית, Mitzrit, but it's also a case about אומות שנתגיירו.
umot shenitgayru. Okay, and we'll see that case, שנתגיירו, shenitgayru, and in
those cases you go by the פגום. pagum. Okay, so yes. And
notice by the way, and this actually gets back to Jenna's question,
all of the exceptions are cases where we're not talking about naturally
born Jews, right? At least one of them, right? Either גר ממזרת,
ger mamzeret, you go by the פגום, pagum, or two nations that
converted, אדומי Edomi and מצרי Mitzri or whatever, you go by the
פגום. pagum. So this still holds true, right, by like naturally born
Jews. I mean, מצרי Mitzri and מצרית Mitzrit is the question about
which category you put it in. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this: האי מאי, hai mai, one minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, how
can you do all of this? אי אמרת בשלמא מתניתין רבי יהודה
היא, iy amart b'shlama matnitin Rabbi Yehuda hi, if our Mishnah's רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda by the מצרי Mitzri and by the גר ger
and the ממזרת, mamzeret, כל מקום דרישא לאתויי ישראל שנשא חללה, kol
makom d'reisha l'atuyei Yisrael shenasa challala, so the כל מקום kol makom
here includes the חללה challala case, okay, דרבה בר בר חנה, d'Rabba
bar bar Chana, and it could also include the דרבה בר בר
חנה d'Rabba bar bar Chana of the מצרי Mitzri and the מצרית
Mitzrit case. Okay, now we're going to go through, like does something
fit into each box? Now that we've established that there are things
that each box creates more things in the category and allows for
exceptions. Okay, so if you say this as this and this as
this, איזו זו למעוטי דרב דימי ורבין, eizo zo l'motei d'Rav Dimi
v'Ravin,
איזו זו eizo zo is either, because now we're working with רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, איזו זו eizo zo is coming to deal with
the exception to the rule of the אומות שנתגיירו umot shenitgayru and
possibly the מצרי Mitzri and the מצרית Mitzrit depending on how you
פסקן. pasken. So we have things that fall into the exception category.
Okay, people sort of following the thrust of this? כל מקום דסיפא,
kol makom d'seifa, now we haven't gotten to this yet, כל מקום
דסיפא לאתויי גר שנשא ממזרת. kol makom d'seifa l'atuyei ger shenasa mamzeret.
And the כל מקום kol makom here, we're dealing with רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, so here there is something that's an application that's not
included. גר ger and ממזרת mamzeret according to him is אין עבירה
ein aveira and it goes by the פגום. pagum. Okay, so we've
got all these categories accounted for. Except not that one. We have
all these categories accounted for. It says, but אלא אי אמרת רבי
יוסי היא, ela iy amart Rabbi Yosi hi, but according to רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, then not all the boxes are filled. כל מקום
דרישא קאמרינן, kol makom d'reisha k'amarin, the כל מקום kol makom here
includes the ישראל Yisrael and the חללה challala and maybe the מצרי
Mitzri and the מצרית Mitzrit case. That's another application of going by
the male. איזו זו, eizo zo, the exception קאמרינן, k'amarin, first of
all it's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi idea that the exception גר ממזרת
ger mamzeret goes by the פגום pagum and all of the אומות
שנתגיירו, umot shenitgayru, all of those are the exception that you go
by the פגום. pagum. אלא כל מקום דסיפא לאתויי מאי? ela kol
makom d'seifa l'atuyei mai? But there's nothing in the סיפא seifa of
when there's an עבירה aveira you go by the פגום pagum that's
not mentioned. So there's nothing else included in the כלל klal that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has, where we're assuming the כל kol is
coming to include Yeah, that's what we're assuming. We're going to answer
that. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda includes in that כל, kol, גר וממזרת.
ger u'mamzeret. It's an עבירה aveira and you go by the פגם,
pgam, but for רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, he doesn't פסקן pasken that
way. So the גמרא Gemara says but you haven't put anything in
this box. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, let's see, the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, ולטעמיך u'l'taimeich רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda איזו זו
דסיפא למה לי? eizo zo d'seifa lamma lei? You don't need something
in every box, says the גמרא. Gemara. You don't have an exception
here for, right, to the הלכה halacha of going after the פגם
pgam when there's an עבירה, aveira, אלא איידי דתנא רישא איזו זו
תנא סיפא איזו זו. Ella aidi d'tana reisha eizo zo, tana seifa
eizo zo. Of course you have those boxes in the first half
of the משנה, Mishna, where we did have more things to include
and things to exclude. We have those boxes in the end. So
הכא נמי איידי דתנא רישא כל מקום תנא סיפא כל מקום. hacha
nami aidi d'tana reisha kol makom, tana seifa kol makom. Okay, יישר
כוח. yasher koach. Alright, that was a little exhausting. Let's try to
do, we'll see if we can get in two more minutes, this
last one more case. גופא, Gufa, כי אתא רבין ki ata Ravin
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, באומות הלך אחר הזכר, b'umos halech
achar hazachar, בגרים הלך אחר פגם שבשניהם. b'geirim halech achar pgam she-bishneihem.
מאי באומות הלך אחר הזכר? Mai b'umos halech achar hazachar? What would
be the case that they're non-Jews, they remain non-Jews, and the tribe
is defined by the father, right? In כנעני, cana'ani, so כי תניא:
ki tanya: מנין לאחד מן האומות שבא על כנענית, minalan l'echad min
ha'umos sheba al cana'anit, a female כנענית, cana'anit, you know, has a
child with somebody from not one of the seven nations, והוליד בן,
v'holid ben, שאתה רשאי לקנותו בעבד? she'ata rasha'i liknoto b'eved? How do
you know that that child of that kid, that kid is not
considered to be a כנעני Cana'ani and you'd be allowed to have
them as a slave and it's not under the מצווה mitzvah of
destroying all the seven Cana'anite nations, that you're not allowed to own
them as slaves etc.? How do you know that child is not
one of the Cana'anite nations if the father is not a כנעני?
cana'ani? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: וגם מבני התושבים הגרים עמכם, vegam mibnei
hatoshavim hagarim imachem, from those that are not so, those that are
dwelling in your land, they're not native to your land, מהם תקנו,
mehem tiknu, you can actually still buy those children as slaves. Okay,
so if they're not native, if they're not native Cana'anites, they're just
dwelling in your land, which is understood to be the, that the
definition of native or not native we're like sort of a little
bit making reading our assumptions into the פסוק. pasuk. We're assuming what
defines that is the father. So if the, if the, if the
person is not native, meaning if the father isn't native, but they're
in the land and they have a wife who's a כנענית, cana'anit,
the child is not a כנענית. cana'anit. יכול אף עבד Yachol af
eved or maybe בכנעני שבא על שפחה מן האומות והוליד בן, b'Cana'ani
sheba al shifcha min ha'umos v'holid ben, שאתה רשאי לקנותו בעבד? she'ata
rasha'i liknoto b'eved? What about the reverse? If it was a כנעני
Cana'ani man who had a child with a non-Cana'anite woman, maybe that
child you'd be allowed to purchase, would not be considered a כנעני?
Cana'ani? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: אשר הולידו בארצכם, asher holidu b'artzechem, you
can buy these slaves from those that are born in your land,
meaning that by haphazardly they're born in your land, that's not really
their identity, their real identity is that they live somewhere else because
their father lives somewhere else. מן הנולדים בארצכם, Min hanoladim b'artzechem, those
you can, אבל לא מן הגרים בארצכם, aval lo min hagarim b'artzechem,
those that live the land, defined by the father. If the father
is, he is from כנען, Cana'an, so the children are basically considered
to be living in כנען Cana'an because they follow the father. So
in that case, you know, it goes by the father. Of course,
you realize what we did is we took our assumptions, we read
into the פסוק pasuk and then we read it back out of
the פסוק, pasuk, right? Because the פסוק pasuk doesn't say anything about
father, whether, it just says there are some people that are, sometimes
they're considered to be, you know, born abroad but living here, and
sometimes they're born here but they're living abroad. And who is that?
Well, it goes by the father. So you see you go by
the father. Anyway, so for the non-Jewish nations, for the non-Jews, the
status of which nation you're a part of is defined by the
father, and we'll continue tomorrow about what happens when they convert and
you deal with an אדומי Edomi convert and a מואבי Moavi convert
or an עמוני Amoni convert and how that works out.